Hi, I'm David Jackson,
an engineering manager on
the UI Frameworks team.
Today, I'll cover how to
bring your app to iPhone Duo.
First, I'll tell you how
to get started in Xcode.
Next, I'll walk through
general layout guidance to make
your app resize correctly
on any platform.
Then, I'll tell you about
specific layout
guidance for iPhone Duo
to make your app truly shine.
Let's get started.
Your app will work
on iPhone Duo even if
you haven't built it
with the iOS 27 SDK.
When the device is closed,
your app will use the screen space
to the left of the
status bar and camera.
When the device is open,
your app will be a familiar
size and aspect ratio.
Here's how to take more advantage
of the available screen space.
If you've already
adopted the iOS 27 SDK,
the work you've done
to support iPhone app
resizing really pays off.
Now your app will look like this.
Your app will extend
to the left of the status bar
area on the inner display.
And here's how to take advantage
of the entire screen space.
When you build your app
with the iOS 27.1 SDK,
your app extends to
the edge of the screen.
Standard navigation
and toolbar buttons now lay out
vertically under the status bar.
To get the full-screen experience,
download Xcode 27.1.
Choose the iPhone Duo simulator
to run your app in Device Hub.
Use the control buttons at
the bottom of the screen
to open,
close, rotate, or fold iPhone Duo.
Now that your app is using
the full screen space,
you may notice some issues
with your layout in each pose.
A great iPhone Duo
app follows flexible
layout best practices we've
discussed in the past.
Most recently,
we covered flexible layout
principles during the talk,
"Modernize Your UIKit
App" from WWDC26.
These principles matter more
than ever for iPhone Duo,
as your app will need to
resize to fit every pose,
opened, closed, rotated, or folded.
iPhone apps have been adapting
to change for a long time.
They've adapted to new screen sizes,
screen shapes,
and special regions
like the Dynamic Island.
iPhone Duo continues along that path
with a new screen shape
and camera location.
With iOS 27,
people can resize your app larger than
ever before using iPhone
Mirroring on the Mac.
Opening and closing iPhone
Duo works the same way.
Your app may react to different
size class boundaries,
but it is still an iPhone app.
The best app layouts are
adaptive across a
continuum of devices.
They avoid making assumptions
about display sizes
or device capabilities based
on user interface idioms.
And they use tools like size classes
to differentiate between
small and large layouts.
Let's talk more about size classes.
Horizontal and vertical size
classes are loosely tied
to the available space in
their given dimensions.
Size classes express the user
experience your app
should provide based
on the available space.
For SwiftUI, use the environment.
For UIKit, use trait collection.
On iPhone Duo, there are
several size class combinations.
On the outer display,
like other iPhone models,
iPhone Duo has regular
vertical size class and
compact horizontal
size class in portrait,
and compact vertical and horizontal
size classes in landscape.
On the inner display,
the additional space lets you
show more content like sidebars.
As such, it has regular horizontal
and vertical size classes.
The interface orientation
on the outer display behaves
like any other iPhone.
iPhone Duo is a great opportunity
to support landscape orientation,
as people may want to set
the phone down like a tent.
Interface orientation on the
inner display behaves differently.
The inner display doesn't honor your
supported interface orientations.
As with Idiom,
avoid checking interface
orientation for layout decisions.
Use size classes instead.
On a device with two displays,
avoid referencing the
main screen in your code.
It's ambiguous and will be
deprecated in a future release.
If possible, don't use
screen references at all.
Instead, use more local
concepts like the environment,
trait collection,
or the scene's bounds.
If you need access to the screen,
access it dynamically
from the window scene.
To make sure your UI fits the
corners of the screen perfectly,
use Concentricity APIs
introduced in iOS 26.
They're updated to work with
the screen shapes on iPhone Duo.
For SwiftUI, use ConcentricRectangle.
For UIKit, use UICornerConfiguration.
iPhone Duo will continue to honor
the UIRequiresFullScreen key,
but your app will still resize
when someone opens or
closes their iPhone Duo.
iPhone Duo respects your
supported interface orientations,
but your app will scale
on the inner display,
including in Split View multitasking.
For more on iPhone Duo screens,
see the companion Tech Talk,
"Leverage multiple displays
and scenes on iPhone Duo."
Now that your app is resizing to
fit the inner and outer displays,
I'll talk about unique layout
considerations for iPhone Duo.
Using standard navigation
patterns is a great way
to adapt to every iPhone Duo pose.
SwiftUI's NavigationSplitView
or UIKit's UISplitViewController
are fully adaptive.
When iPhone Duo is closed,
columns will collapse to
single-stack navigation.
When open,
columns will appear both
tiled and as overlays.
SwiftUI's TabView
and UIKit's
UITabBarController also adapt
to all poses.
By default, tabs will appear
on the inner and outer display,
laying out vertically
when appropriate.
On the inner display,
you can opt into a sidebar
with richer navigation.
For SwiftUI, set the default
tab bar placement to sidebar.
For UIKit, set the preferred
placement to sidebar.
Sheets also adapt to all poses.
On the outer display, sheets can
have buttons that lay out vertically.
On the inner display,
sheets are centered.
Other presentations like
popovers, context menus,
and alerts also adapt to each pose.
Navigation bars, toolbars,
and tab bars lay out
outside the safe area.
They automatically avoid
system UI like the status bar
and hardware features like the camera.
Horizontal bars provide
top and bottom insets,
while vertical bars provide
leading and trailing insets.
For a deep dive on
vertically arranged content,
check out the companion tech talk,
"Raise the Bar with iPhone Duo".
Respecting safe areas ensures
your app's controls are reachable
and your app is fully visible.
Here's how to best adopt
safe areas in your app.
When positioning your UI,
make sure to place foreground elements
like interactive controls
within the safe area.
For SwiftUI,
your content is placed within
the safe area by default.
For UIKit, if you are
laying out views manually,
reference the view's safe area insets,
or use Auto Layout to
constrain the views
to the safe area layout guide.
Allow background elements
such as full-bleed artwork
to fill the available space,
extending behind
toolbars and sidebars.
For SwiftUI, use ignoresSafeArea.
For UIKit, use the view's bounds.
Keep in mind that safe
areas are often asymmetric.
This is especially true on iPhone Duo.
For example, vertical buttons can
appear on the left side in landscape
and Split View multitasking.
As such,
avoid assuming that insets
on opposite sides are equal.
Instead, write code that
handles each side independently.
As with safe areas,
layout margins are also asymmetric.
This lets your foreground
content get closer
to vertical buttons
and the status bar,
while preserving the margin
on the opposite side.
It's important to test
your handling of safe areas
in different configurations.
Split View multitasking
is no exception.
Using Device Hub, preview
your app on the inner display.
Drag your app using the
home indicator at the bottom
to one side of the screen.
An area to drop your app appears.
Then, drag your app to the other side.
Vertically laid-out content can
appear on either side of your app.
Lastly, in iOS 27.1,
we're introducing a new API
that lets your custom UI use
as much of the available screen space
as possible without colliding
with system-provided UI.
For SwiftUI,
use ReservedRegion
to safely position UI
elements outside the safe area
while maximizing usable space.
For UIKit, it's called
UIViewReservedRegion.
This is a great option
for building your own custom bars
or when implementing edge-to-edge UI.
For more information
on reserved regions,
including how you can use them
to build custom UI that
adapts to the fold,
see the companion Tech Talk,
"Strike a Pose with Adaptive
Layouts on iPhone Duo."
To summarize safe area best practices,
use standard bars for UI
that automatically
adapts to the safe area.
Align your interactive
or visible foreground
content to the safe area,
while background content may
extend past the safe area.
Make sure to account for, and test,
asymmetrical safe areas
and layout margins.
If you have more complex layouts,
consider using reserved regions.
I covered a lot of adaptive
layout best practices.
Here's an efficient way to make
sure your app follows all of them.
During the talk,
Modernize Your UIKit App,
we introduced a new app
modernization skill.
With Xcode 27.1,
this skill has a new name:
App Resizability.
It now supports
SwiftUI and iPhone Duo.
Give it a try.
Now your app is ready to feel
right at home on iPhone Duo.
To recap, download Xcode 27.1,
simulate your app
on iPhone Duo using Device Hub,
make sure your app follows all
the adaptive layout best
practices I covered,
and try out the App
Resizability skill.
And that's it.
Thank you so much for your time.
I look forward to seeing your
iPhone Duo app above the fold
on the App Store.